Speaker 1: China's economy is, quote, slowing sharply as the trade ward enters its fifth month, while every other major trade partner has made a deal with Trump.
Speaker 1: Across the board, China's retail sales are slowing, industrial production missed expectations, investment is crawling at just half a percent, the worst since the 2020 pandemic.
Speaker 1: Urban joblessness, which is the only kind China cares about, is about a fifth higher than the U.S.
Speaker 1: Youth unemployment is nearly 18 percent, up three points in a single month.
Speaker 1: Still, the numbers are not as bad as many predicted.
Speaker 1: Unlike Mexico or Germany, China is not crashing.
Speaker 1: Now, this could be fake.
Speaker 1: China is famous for massaging statistics on a scale that puts our lying Bureau of Labor Statistics to shame.
Speaker 1: As the New York Times puts it, quote, China's ability to tightly control information has prevented unfettered conversations about the toll inflicted by the trade war.
Speaker 1: Did China stop publishing hundreds of economic statistics once the trade war began?
Speaker 1: Still, China's out in free fall for two reasons, stimulus and dumping.
Speaker 1: So far, China's dumped 1.6 trillion of stimulus to dull the pain, along with unconventional moves, like forcing 867,000 state-owned firms to buy their own shares, and, quote, investigating private brokerages who also sell shares.
Speaker 1: Second, China's actually increased exports to everybody but the U.S.
Speaker 1: Now, big hunk is tariff evasion, where Chinese ships stop in Vietnam, unload and reload, keep going to L.A., and presto, it's a Vietnam import.
Speaker 1: But another hunk is dumping the stuff they can't sell in America, below cost, into Europe and the third world.
Speaker 1: So, Temu's Latin American shipments have soared 143% this year.
Speaker 1: There was a recent uproar in Indonesia about Chinese jeans selling for 80 cents.
Speaker 1: None of this is sustainable.
Speaker 1: Trump's new deals are explicitly targeting reshipments, while countries are already pushing back on Chinese dumping.
Speaker 1: The EU imposed new tariffs on Chinese electric vehicles.
Speaker 1: India is targeting Chinese steel.
Speaker 1: Mexico is targeting Chinese cars.
Speaker 1: In fact, China knows it's not sustainable, recently moving to starve marginal factories of capital to reduce overcapacity, in other words, to shut them down.
Speaker 1: In short, China has so far avoided the worst, assuming you believe, official numbers, but it's running out of runway on both stimulus and dumping.
Speaker 1: Now, China has 40 days, until November 11th, to make a deal with Trump or tariffs jump back to 145% up from 30% today.
Speaker 1: The outstanding issues include barriers to American food, energy, and services, forced tech transfers,
Speaker 1: where China forces foreign companies to share tech and even train their competitors,
Speaker 1: along with so-called industrial policy, where Beijing gives cheap money to exporters.
Speaker 1: And Trump being Trump, he will probably want guaranteed Chinese purchases of American goods.
Speaker 1: Last time around, it was $200 billion, which they never bought using COVID as the excuse.
Speaker 1: So as sags brought to buy, I trust capital.
Speaker 1: Both sides seem motivated.
Speaker 1: China backed off a ban on rare earth exports, which are used to make American weapons.
Speaker 1: A single F-35 contains a half ton of rare earths.
Speaker 1: Meanwhile, China's rhetoric has been uncharacteristically tame.
Speaker 1: They're no longer calling Trump a self-serving narcissistic bandit.
Speaker 1: For his part, Trump just postponed a planned arms sale to Taiwan and could even shift America's Taiwan stance from neutrality to opposing independence,
Speaker 1: which is a holy grail for China.
Speaker 1: So most likely, they will come to an agreement by November.
Speaker 1: And if they don't, China goes from a 30% tariff slowdown to a 145% collapse.
Speaker 1: Okay, we'll be watching.
Speaker 1: See you next time.